<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal Blog</title>
    <description>Archive of personal blog</description>
    <link>/pblog/</link>
    <atom:link href="/pblog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 14:43:17 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 14:43:17 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>2020</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;The year&lt;/span&gt;  that started in March.
&lt;label for=&quot;mn-source&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;mn-source&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;The idea for this post came while reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/christmas-specials/2020/12/19/christmas-newsletters-are-a-form-of-slow-social-media&quot;&gt;this The Economist’s piece&lt;/a&gt; about Christmas newsletters. &lt;/span&gt;
There have been many metaphors to describe these past nine months. The one I
found most fitting (heard at some point on a Zoom call, a landmark of the
pandemic) is that this all felt to me like I had been forced into a long-haul
flight, with all the limitations, lack of comfort, and dislike that comes with
flying; but somehow I was thrown on business class, while many people found
themeselves in economy, or in some new, worse (under-)class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Privilege&lt;/span&gt;  is a word that has resonated a lot and stayed
with me over this year. Part of it is the extremely uneven nature of the 
pandemic, where front workers and some parts of society are living the biggest
disruption to life since WWII, while many of us can barely “do our part” and
stay home, wash our hands and wear a mask. Part is also the exposure, laid
bare a bit more this year, of much longer-standing inequalities in society and
my position/role in each of them. The first step to action is acknowledgement,
and 2020 has provided plenty of “nudge” in that direction. I have started to
re-evaluate my role and position of power in many of these contexts and I hope 
I can &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; more in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Such an unusual&lt;/span&gt;  year has made me miss many things. 
At the risk of sounding obvious, “social distancing” has put distance between
people. Visiting family, hugging friends, interacting with students, and
direct exchanges with colleagues are all things we have had to “do” through
the mediation of a screen this year. 
For someone who pays close attention to cities as a job, I have found
both fascinating and terrifying how the pandemic has turned urban spaces
upside down, &lt;label for=&quot;sn-cities&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sn-cities&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1271819847706558471&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; was my (failed) speculative take on
what cities would become during the pandemic. &lt;/span&gt; and how the
“core tech” that makes cities one of our best inventions –bringing people
together– was disabled on purpose during most of this year.
Although it has been formative to discover
how much modern technology allows (the equivalent in the 1918 flu pandemic
sure was less fun!), I can’t wait to go back to a world where that is &lt;em&gt;an&lt;/em&gt;
option rather than &lt;em&gt;the only&lt;/em&gt; one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;I have also missed&lt;/span&gt;  travelling a lot. My travel was 
so full just before the pandemic that the first weeks docked home felt good, very
good. 
&lt;label for=&quot;sn-01&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sn-01&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;The fantastic weather the UK saw this spring and the
back garden (privilege, again) that let us get a patch of greenery to read in
also helped inmensely. &lt;/span&gt; But, as the days passed, I started remembering everything I like about
travelling, missing the places I was meant to visit again, and the new ones I
would have discovered. As the year progressed, I found myself even missing
early rises to catch a 6am train on my way to London just for the day, the
rush and adrenaline of having &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt; to go, and &lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; to meet.
If there
is a silverlining in all this is that we miss what we love, and some of
these aspects were probably too taken for granted to be fully appreciated.
Maybe the new year will mean a “reset” that’ll make me live more fully in the 
future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;But&lt;/span&gt;  2020 was not entirely lost. There has been some good
out of this forced change of routines. 
Less trains, planes and trips has meant a bit more time in Liverpool, and
lockdowns made sure that was spent mostly laying around the house. One of the
most consistently rewarding ways I have found to fill that space and time has
been through narrative. One could argue I read for a living, but this year I
have read for fun more than I thought I’d be able.
&lt;label for=&quot;sn-twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sn-twitter-thread&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/darribas/status/1340979325269667842&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a list with a few picks.
 &lt;/span&gt;
And it’s been great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Less work travel&lt;/span&gt;  has also allowed me to have a bit more 
space to think and be less reactive about how I plan my work. I have worked
hard on two big projects&lt;label for=&quot;sn-book-ati&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sn-book-ati&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;One is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://geographicdata.science&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; and the other one a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.turing.ac.uk/research/research-projects/urban-grammar&quot;&gt;big “endeavour”&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt; 
that I don’t think I’d have been able to find the time and mindspace to focus 
on in the way I have this year.
And on the topic of work, I can’t wait to see what happens to all this tech and 
practices we have rolled out to keep universities, teaching and research going, 
while distributed and remote. 
&lt;label for=&quot;sn-uni&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sn-uni&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Back in March, we joked with colleagues that, had the University
announced in January a plan to move teaching delivery to 80%-100% online in
the next two years, we would have all thought it was a pipe dream; yet, two
months later, we all silently made it happen pretty much in two weeks… &lt;/span&gt;
Once it’s not the only option, I think a lot of
good will come from having proven it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Taken altogether&lt;/span&gt; , this has been quite the year. The most
unusual and unprecedented in many ways, yet the most boring in others. As we
have just stepped into a 2021 full of promises and hope, &lt;em&gt;what do I want
to take with me from 2020?&lt;/em&gt; As a major fan of the rule of three, I’ll take
that many.
The first is the liberating sense of resilience I felt when both collectively 
as a society and individually as myself, we were able to “reinvent” ourselves
and continue doing things that either needed to be done or we wanted to do,
just in slightly different ways.
The second is the power of habit. When you don’t have to go anywhere and your
commute takes the distance that connects your kitchen to the living room,
there’s the risk that you’re fooled to believe you have “all the time there
is”. Finding a good routine and sticking to it have proven extremely valuable.
And finally, perhaps the most obvious one, the pandemic has taught me to take
as little for granted as possible, because it almost never is. From being able
to ride the whole thing with E, to family, friends and work colleagues,
this year has made even clearer how lucky I am, how grateful I should be, and
how much good I should work to put &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; into the world. And, if I can take
even just a little bit of that with me into 2021, then maybe it has not been
that terrible of a year.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/articles/21/2020</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/articles/21/2020</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>(Pre) Birthday girl</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ift.tt/2xngSqv&quot;&gt;http://ift.tt/2xngSqv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
via &lt;a href=&quot;http://ift.tt/1c4nCfM&quot;&gt;IFTTT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2017 13:34:49 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2017/08/27/pre-birthday-girl/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2017/08/27/pre-birthday-girl/</guid>
        
        <category>Instagram</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New York 2,140</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;[...] To her data analysis was the ugly love child of science and Kafka, always either proving the sky was blue or demonstrating the truth of something deeply wrong or, to be more precise, radically counterintuitive to Gen Octaviasdottir. And Gen was all about intuition. So this was a tool that cut her as much as the material she was working on. Nevertheless it was often useful [...]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&quot;Inspector Gen&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;Kim Stanley Robinson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;New York 2,140&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 13:57:29 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2017/08/21/new-york-2140/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2017/08/21/new-york-2140/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Requiem para mi yaya</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;No creo que la sociedad laica occidental hoy en día, entre la que me cuento a mi mismo, sepa afrontar la muerte de manera satisfactoria. Siendo la vida una carrera sin fin a más -a obtener más, a hacer más, a acumular más- dejar de existir supone el fracaso último. En vida, la gente lleva a cabo todo tipo de aberraciones con tal de disimular, de pretender que el tiempo no pasa y que, independientemente del dinero, experiencias, y oportunidades que hayamos tenido, al final todos terminamos igual. Pero, si el ser humano es poderoso, la naturaleza lo es más, y al final todos tenemos que afrontar la inevitable &quot;derrota&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mi abuela Antonia vivió sus ultimos años entre dos mundos. Por un lado, la España de finales del s.XX, en la que salía a comprar y a la peluquería por la mañana, hacía la comida y, por la tarde, iba de paseo con mi abuelo hasta mi casa o la de mis primos para vernos jugar, hacer los deberes y, en general, crecer felices. Era una vida en la que, con todas sus complejidades, problemas e imperfecciones, creo que se sentía cómoda. Y, si no, siempre estaban los veranos largos en el pueblo. Sobretodo desde que murió mi abuelo, ese mundo se desvaneció poco a poco, y su lugar lo ocupó una realidad que, con razón, le costaba entender. Un mundo en el que no solo mi hermano, mis primos y yo estabamos irreconociblemente crecidos, sino que casi todos los elementos que habían hecho su existencia feliz, o habían muerto o se habían convertido en obsoletos recuerdos en papel sepia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Es por ello que no creo que mi abuela, en la sabiduría que solo los años otorgan, afrontase la muerte la pasada noche como un fracaso. Religiosa, como todo el mundo en la Espana que le vio nacer, espero que cerrase los ojos por última vez con la satisfaccion del trabajo bien hecho (como siempre nos decía de pequeños), y con la tranquilidad de quien sabe que el descanso es bien merecido. Mientras escribo estas lineas a la vez que escucho el &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tmrQHRnT4Mw&quot;&gt;Requiem de Faure&lt;/a&gt;, no puedo evitar recordar sus palabras acerca del inusual tono brillante de una obra escrita para acompañar a la muerte:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt;Pero es asi que veo la muerte: como una liberación feliz, una aspiración hacia la felicidad ahi arriba, mas que como una experiencia dolorosa&lt;/em&gt;&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2016 23:37:43 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2016/08/07/requiem-para-mi-yaya/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2016/08/07/requiem-para-mi-yaya/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Haydn</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;No composer had ever been left to develop so peacefully and with so many resources at his command than Haydn, who acknowledged, “My Prince was always satisfied with my works; I not only had the encouragement of constant approval, but as conductor of an orchestra, I could make experiments, observe what produced an effect and what weakened it, and was thus in a position to improve, alter, make additions or omissions, and be as bold as I pleased. I was cut off from the world, there was no one to confuse or torment me, and I was forced to become original.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;The Essential Cannon of Classical Music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;David Dubal&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 00:03:26 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2016/08/02/haydn/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2016/08/02/haydn/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Olvido</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;¿Cómo era una entrada de cine, un billete de tren, un pasaje de avión hace 20 o 30 años, un taxímetro, una de esas hojas de publicidad que se reparten por la calle y todo el mundo tira en la papelera más próxima? ¿Cómo era el ruido de fondo de lo cotidiano, las sintonías de los programas de radio, las voces de los anuncios y las de los locutores de los telediarios, el empaquetado de los productos de limpieza, la estética de la publicidad de coches? Olería fuertemente a tabaco en los trenes, en los autobuses, en las oficinas, en los bares, hasta en los aviones, pero casi ninguno de nosotros se daba cuenta.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;firstHeading&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cultura.elpais.com/cultura/2016/01/06/babelia/1452084955_815353.html&quot;&gt;Formas de olvido.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;firstHeading&quot; class=&quot;firstHeading&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;Antonio Muñoz Molina. Enero 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2016 12:48:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2016/02/06/olvido/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2016/02/06/olvido/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ventanas con vistas</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Gracias a &lt;a href=&quot;http://elpais.com/diario/2011/04/30/babelia/1304122338_850215.html&quot;&gt;Muñoz Molina&lt;/a&gt; llego en esta mañana de sábado, lenta a ritmo de café y tostada, a esta &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metmuseum.org/exhibitions/listings/2011/rooms-with-a-view/photo-gallery&quot;&gt;exposición&lt;/a&gt; del Met. Entre todas las fotografías, la del &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pubhist.com/w12309&quot;&gt;estudio&lt;/a&gt; de Giovanni Battista de Gubernatis capta mi atención.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gubernatis was an official in the Napoleonic administration who painted in his spare time. When his transfer from northern Italy to France became imminent in 1812, he painted this view of his studio. It is both an inventory and a souvenir of a beloved room he was about to leave behind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inmediatamente, ese pie de foto me recuerda esta otra imagen que tomé de la mesa de trabajo en mi casa de Tempe hace unos años:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dreamessenceonthemove.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/tempe_house.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone wp-image-685 size-large&quot; src=&quot;/pblog/assets/2015/10/tempe_house.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;tempe_house&quot; width=&quot;660&quot; height=&quot;495&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;A la vez inventario y recuerdo de la habitación que estaba a punto de dejar atrás&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 14:08:40 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2015/10/17/ventanas-con-vistas/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2015/10/17/ventanas-con-vistas/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Anniversary</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dreamessenceonthemove.files.wordpress.com/2015/06/wpid-wp-1435619333800.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img title=&quot;wp-1435619333800&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;/pblog/assets/2015/06/wpid-wp-1435619333800.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grand Canyon National Park.&lt;br /&gt;
Part of &lt;em&gt;Génesis&lt;/em&gt;, by Sebastião Salgado.&lt;br /&gt;
Caixaforum Zaragoza. June 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 02:13:58 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2015/06/30/anniversary/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2015/06/30/anniversary/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Public water</title>
        <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;Rome, Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;June 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2015 14:21:33 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2015/06/22/public-water/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2015/06/22/public-water/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>&quot;Twitterhoods&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://unibirmingham.tumblr.com/post/119013810163/does-twitter-make-us-view-cities-differently&quot;&gt;reposted&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Birmingham's official Tumbler. This text was prepared in the lead to the Pint of Science event in Birmingham, where I also &lt;a href=&quot;http://pintofscience.co.uk/event/big-data-cities/&quot;&gt;presented&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all know what a neighbourhood is, right? It’s a part of a city that shares a common character and feel, either defined by the people who live, work or visit there. The problem comes when you try to put it on a map, then it becomes much harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, for the most part, the study of cities has been constrained by “given” boundaries such as postcodes, which actually have very little meaning in themselves. This is about to change, thanks to the data and computational revolutions currently underway. This will open up many doors to explore different methods to quantify, visualize and imagine the city in radically new ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take Twitter, for example. The language in which a tweet is posted reveals a host of information about its “poster”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tweets in uncommon languages likely come from members of ethnic minorities; or tweets in English posted in non-english speaking countries can signal a more cosmopolitan author. If we combine this simple piece of metadata, with the location where the tweet was sent, it is possible to relate different languages to different parts of a city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Areas where only the local language is spoken are likely to be very different from those where a variety of languages coexist. Touristy areas, for example, will have a relatively smaller proportion of local tweets and a larger share of foreign posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although a person can start to imagine how these different maps overlay and reveal the character of each area, it is difficult for the human brain to process all the information at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, this is one of the tasks that a properly taught (programmed) computer can do very well. Using a family of techniques called machine learning, a computer can process all the tweets in a city and return a map that summarizes them into neighbourhoods. These neighbourhoods contain much more substantive meaning than the ones we are accustomed to use (e.g. post codes or administrative boundaries), and provide a representation of the city that, although we’ve always know was there, we could not picture. How cool is that?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 11:35:41 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/pblog/2015/05/23/twitterhoods/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pblog/2015/05/23/twitterhoods/</guid>
        
        <category>big data</category>
        
        <category>pint of science</category>
        
        <category>pint15</category>
        
        <category>twitter</category>
        
        <category>university</category>
        
        
        <category>English</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
